I really feel that there is this
collective subconscious rage that is
just boiling in women and it's coming up
in so many ways we see we see in the
media and and what's going on is this
unknown rage that comes up in in many
different ways
um and on one hand it needs to come out
we need to clear it it needs to be
expressed it needs to be acknowledged on
the other hand it's not enough this is
only like this is breaking the ice so
that the next step of evolution can you
know consciousness can start coming
through and that's what I'm lacking in
women it's really to take responsibility
for what we do as women in our
manipulation in our seduction in our
control and and it's so easy for women
to say but that's just because we're
angry and men did this and patriarchy
but it's it's such a lack of
responsibility and this women really
need to know because we could say we
could look at say me too which has been
kind of ongoing for a long time and as
still a massive force and we can say
that it's it's brought up a lot of male
shadows it's brought showing up a lot of
male behavior that is just inexcusable
should not happen and it's it's
certainly you could say started as a
positive thing but then you also have
like there's there's perhaps a danger of
it's slipping into a very simplistic
narrative of men as only aggressors
women as only victims is that something
that you're worried about I'm very
worried about that because what it feels
like is it has displayed the male shadow
but who talks about the female shadow
the rage that that women are expressing
blindly and projecting onto which ever
situation and whichever men that they
can this is this is where women need to
step up and take responsibility and stop
blaming men it's pointless
we need to transcend this we can't solve
this we can't solve this problem from
the steps from the same level we need to
transcend and look at how am i adding to
this dynamic as a woman because we are
we are co-creating it in perfect harmony
if women are angry we absolutely need to
take responsibility for getting
ourselves to another place I mean that's
the the kind of shadow work is the
acceptance that we all have shadows that
men certainly have a shadow there is a
shadow around masculinity but there's
also a shadow around femininity and
while part of the cultural conversation
now is toxic masculinity and everyone
knows what you mean by toxic toxic
masculinity if you talk about toxic
femininity everyone still knows what you
mean but you can't have that
conversation which is it's it's
interesting what is allowed to be said
and what is not allowed to be said at
the moment and that Dad I think is is
very dangerous that certain topics
certain conversations are off are
off-limits and this is where we see
where we see the victim persecutor
dynamics activates it because women
become the become the victims and we
make ourselves the victims and we
persecute men but in that aggression in
that reach and when we are the victims
we are in perfect control we become the
persecutors because we say it's all
about blame men did this and men need to
take responsibility but in that we
become the persecutors it's also a
problem with the media because the short
attention span of the media wants to
polarize things and it's a very is
therefore very easy like it's a very
straightforward narrative victim
perpetrated and yet the true dynamics
needs something more than just a very
short analysis or a soundbite it needs
to be unpacked over time and it needs to
be it's easily taken out of context
which is why it's such a hot potato for
the media to handle I think it's also
it's a very very old story about you
cannot say
to a woman in the public debate take
responsibility for the for what you're
doing take responsibility for the role
that you're playing into and and I want
to talk for a moment about the
President's Club I don't know very much
about the details but I I think that
women in this country when we enter the
room we have an absolute right to put up
a boundary we have an ability to put up
a boundary and say I'm not gonna play
this game
I'm not going to co-create these
antagonism between men and women I'm not
gonna co-create this patriarchal
structure and be a victim if if if I if
I'm working in a bar somewhere somewhere
and someone is groping me I have the
responsibility on the right to say stop
it right now go to my manager have that
person kicked out or walk out of the
room no one needs to be a victim and
this is what women just simply don't
want to hear they don't want to take
responsibility for we are co-creating it
we like being the victims we like
blaming men instead of doing our own
work and say what am i getting from this
whole seduction control manipulation I
get power the power of the victim and
it's it's it's the easy power it's the
cheap power and it's not long-lasting we
really need to have this conversation in
a balanced way mmm because I started
teaching men's work maybe a year ago or
so and the REE the biggest reason for
that was I could see a need for it
individually and among a lot of the men
that I know but also because culturally
it just felt like this was a time when
men were being challenged to step up to
evolve as men to integrate our shadows
to kind of to be confronted with sort of
the negative traits of masculinity and
to integrate them and move forward but I
know that some people might look at
men's work and say oh it's divisive what
you're doing is kind of perpetuating the
patriarchy for example what do you think
of that as a criticism it's it's a
really good question because
in my experience when I when I work with
men and women for me it's very obvious
that that women really relate to
self-development and to to to go in deep
emotionally in themselves where I feel
men Imoh vague or not as on it and it
might be that I'm a woman and that men
want more more kind of safe environment
when where there's only men to do that
but I feel that men have been somehow
lacking in in really engaging with their
own personal development really taking
responsibility for for their belief
patterns for their for their emotions
for how they show up in the world
and in my work I feel that I'm going
deep in womanhood what does it mean to
be a woman this is what interests me
this is what I'm passionate about it's
it's about the deep feminine and women
are drawn to that so many women come to
me and say thank you for showing up in
the world like this now I'm getting a
sense of something that hasn't I I
haven't had it modeled you know in my
therapy practice we talk a lot about
childhood and how are your parents and
and so few women have had muddled a
healthy feminine so that's what I'm
passionate about
but in that work I feel I've gotten to a
point in my life where I'm thinking
where's men I don't know about men I
don't know what's going on for them I
can't feel them
I don't feel they're showing up I know
I'm talking very general but this is
what I feel it's a lack a lack of
willingness to show up with a woman that
is present and this is what I'm missing
this is why I feel men's work is so
important because women are trying to do
their work and there's a lot to do still
I really want to admit that but men need
to show up and right now there's one man
here and one men there but most men out
there are boys still and I'm sad to say
it but I feel and
women are girls so we're both sides we
have so much work to do
I'd always found men's work really
helpful I've done a lot of self
development work but what I really found
with the men's work was that landing in
my masculinity landing with other men
feeling comfortable in in myself around
other men healing those wounds then
really allowed me to meet women on a
much more from a much more grounded
place and I found my relationships with
women improving with the amount of men's
work that I've been doing and so I
really wanted to start leading men's
work and bring that kind of work to
other men and then my background as a
journalist I've always been very
interested in in kind of following the
media and then I saw those same dynamics
playing out in the political sphere the
Trump Hillary election was just so
clearly from my perspective that we're
so desperate for genuine masculine
values and so missing them that somehow
some strange caricature and facsimile of
genuine masculine values people are
voting for and suddenly this guy who's a
boy pretending to be a man is the most
powerful man in the world so these these
these dynamics are playing out in all of
our lives and then on the wider scale
it's it's quite astonishing to see that
I think that there was perfectly
highlighting the sickness of
post-modernism that we have completely
we have we needed to smash the values so
post-modernism is is is a good thing but
we cannot stay there we've smashed the
values no one knows what it is to be a
man and no one knows what it is to be a
woman and we see these caricatures we
see someone stepping up and doing
something oh let's go that way because
we've lost ground men have lost ground
women have lost ground we're calling for
a more empowered feminine that's like in
the world
Oh patriarchy now we need to call in the
deep feminine but what about the
masculine we see an absolute caricature
of a man being so powerful in the world
because it's exactly where we are if we
don't change this is what we get so
we're getting it's a very very healthy
lesson for the world to see if we don't
start changing this is our future we've
arrived to that future what are we going
to do about that
and also I think it's important to say
that what I'm talking about and I think
you can tell me if it's what you're
talking about as well it's not about
going back to the old masculine feminine
dynamics it not it's not saying men have
to be stereotypically masculine women
have to be stereotypically feminine it's
going through this kind of gender
neutral space and re embracing this sort
of our feminine and masculine essence
and playing those roles out more
consciously for me it's like an
evolutionary step I absolutely agree we
need to go through this we need to to
pull everything apart but we need to put
it together again and say we never have
the the the truth where is the truth the
truth is always changing we we are in a
stream of evolution we never arrive at
that place but we need to keep
questioning and we need to put together
those pieces that makes that create
solid ground for us that creates these
these maps that we so that we know where
to go so we have role models we have we
have people we have values that we
resonate with so so we're not just lost
and we see that even I'm from
Scandinavia and Scandinavia is one of
the places in the world that has the
highest amount of gender equality but
what also happens is that we see as
somehow gender neutral space where men
and women are the same and it has it's
so important to move through that but
especially many friends about sex yes
exactly
men are completely losing their identity
and losing their power they are losing
they're losing the essence of
masculinity and women are somehow taking
that over and getting bitter and
resentful about it so at the surface it
looks like a really equal society but in
terms of relationship
in terms of polarity it's not working
very well
you watch the Jordan Peterson Kathy
Newman interview what did he what did he
think oh I
my whole body contracted and I I felt so
sad for womanhood I felt disappointed
and I could see how the shadow part of
womanhood was acting out I could see how
the collective rage was acting through
Kathy Newman and this is what happens is
that when that's unknown its projected
blindly on to whatever stick wherever it
sticks and it was very clear that she
already had an agenda and she already
had a projection that she was just
looking to state she was she was just
looking to have that confirmed and she
was trying so hard and I felt this was
just a classical example of feminine
manipulation of the deep shadow
manipulation control abuse so I felt on
behalf of women I felt sad and
disappointed because we need to have
intelligent conversations that that that
is aligned with the evolutionary stream
that is aligned with creating a future
not destroying but finding those values
have an intelligent conversation and in
that sense I would have loved to see
Jordan Peterson become present with that
in that moment and say okay I want to
timeout from the debate that we are
having and I want to explore what's
actually going on right here
because I can feel you're coming with a
lot of anger and I think it's important
that that anger gets acknowledged but
that we become real with what's going on
and say it's a projection I understand
why it's there
but I would like us to find a way to
move through it this is what we need as
men and women instead of blindly
projecting our rage on to whoever man
shows up for it
and you said before something about that
she came in as a victim but but under
the surface was abuse it was about it I
felt it was absolutely abusive that she
was manipulating everything that he was
saying she was manipulating it into into
the image she had in her head and she
would just twist what he was saying and
she would not listen so it was not a
conversation it was it was a power game
and she was the abuser and I I felt
cringy on behalf of women that this is
not an empowered woman this is not the
empowered feminine this is the
underbelly of feminism this is when
feminism goes wrong this is not the
future it's not the future to blame and
to project and to persecute can you
explain what you mean a bit more about
when feminism goes wrong when feminism
goes wrong we allow the collective rage
to act out through us so we see every
situation we see every man we'd see
every encounter with the lens of of the
victim and we're so angry about it and
it's it's boiling in every woman it's
right under the surface so she will
quickly snap if if this if there's a
reason or if there's an apparent reason
because it's so strong it hasn't
discharged it's in the collective and
that rage needs to discharge but it
needs to discharge in an intelligent way
not in an unconscious way and you said
before that that rage is often directed
at men not showing up I'd say it's it's
two-way because yes it's it's targeted
at men not showing up or they are
causing it but it's very often projected
out to men that are actually trying to
show up that is actually engaging and we
will engaging with women and actually
talking about these things so that's
that's because then we we bring up this
topic and then it's so easy for women to
tap into that collective pool of rage
and it it just comes out and it's also
very difficult as well because one
imagines that that combative attitude is
something that has served her well in
the past and it's something that she's
maybe felt forced into because of the
nature of the society that she's
operating in so it's a kind of catch-22
situation for the many successful women
because they feel that they're pushed to
be more masculine and then when they're
more masculine they get judged for being
more masculine it's it's very sad and
and and I can see that dynamics being
played out absolutely but I think the
only thing we can do is to take
responsibility and say okay I'm doing
that do I really want to compromise my
femininity do I want to compromise my
integrity
do I want to compromise my gender and
play that or is there another way that I
can be powerful without being aggressive
without playing a power game but resting
in my natural power resting in my
natural dignity resting in that deep
rootedness that we both have in our
genders that when we are peace with it
and when we acknowledge it in ourselves
it's there as a natural thing and this
is the thing I don't want to make this
personal about Kathy Newman because it's
it's in that potential is in every woman
but it's because we are persecuting our
own femininity what's being played out
that we're doing it to ourselves because
we don't trust that it's good enough to
be a woman we don't trust that we can
have conversations that come from a felt
embodied perspective we don't trust that
we're connected to truth because these
these masculine ways have been have been
very strong and women have been denying
their own power and I also want to say
that this isn't even though the the
specific example is the Kathy Newman
Jordan Peters an interview it's not
specific to to Kathy Newman I think the
fact that that interview has resonated
with so many people that it's been so
popular shows that actually something
archetypal was going on in that in that
interaction and I think as well why it's
gone viral is a lot of people watching
it recognize those dynamics they're like
I've been in conversations like that
I've been in this conversation where
nothing
but nothing I say gets through so
there's something sort of fundamental
about about the masculine feminine
dynamic that's going on in there what do
you think that is I think Jordan
Peterson
he's everyman Kathy Newman she's every
woman I can tap into that rage like this
I know it in myself and women that say
they don't they're just denying it
because it is in the collective so in
that sense it just highlighted what
what's there it's wonderful because here
we really get to look at why is this so
important why is it so important to
listen to to a thinker like Jordan
Peterson and take it seriously and say
what can we do with it it's just so
obvious that it's needed because if this
is where we are if this is where society
and cultures is if this is the ability
to have an intelligent conversations
conversation then we are in trouble in
the interview that I did with Jordan
Peterson he said that the Animus
possessed woman which is the woman who
sort of inner masculine side is a kind
of defense for the feminine side sees
every man or project onto every man the
patriarchy the tyrannical King and the
way out of that to see it from a Jungian
perspective that the masculine archetype
has both sides the masculine archetype
is both the tyrannical senile king and
the benevolent father at the same time
and so that they're multi-layered and
you can see either side and in in any
man but the animus possessed woman only
sees one side and that is the patriarchy
that is a tyrannical system that is
something that just needs to be
destroyed does that make a lot of sense
to you I feel that's that's precisely
what's going on it's this blind
projection that makes every man in the
situation it it create it makes it into
an image so and and and that that image
is where all the rage can go so I I
would absolutely agree with that but
another thing I want to say is that that
rage that is just waiting for an outlet
also has also is important information
in in the sense that it needs to be
heard it
needs to be acknowledged and it is also
there because women haven't found a way
to be in our power which is not
necessarily the way of the mind and the
way of having an intellectual
conversation about something it's about
coming back to the body and it's about
coming back to feeling the energy of
what's going on and really trusting that
we know in our body a deep truth that
cannot necessarily be met or
acknowledged in an intellectual
conversation and because women have not
been able to articulate that deep truth
that deep wisdom that deep power that's
also where the rage comes because we
know that deep down there's something
that hasn't been seen and acknowledged
and by men and we're so angry about that
but we just forget that we have to start
with ourselves and to say okay I feel
something is going on here how can we
address this in an intelligent way that
is not just pure philosophy and it's not
just a pure intellectual conversation
but it's in touch with what's real it's
in touch with life it's in touch with
co-creating evolution co-creating
consciousness and we can't do that
only in an intellectual conversation
where we just we just we're just arguing
against each other shadows it's not
really symbolic
completely yes an ideological conscious
yeah that reminds me of something that
I've heard before that men test ideas
and women test men and there's some
truth in that from what you're saying
it's like because women know on a deeper
level than men and women know when men
are out of alignment on a much more
deeper level than men often do and so
there is something about women's
embodied way of knowing and a genuine
it's a it's a very you it's it's
essential for women to test men it's
like so how aligned are you and that I
think is what is playing out on the
wider the wider culture this the
excesses
of feminism you could say our men being
tested on an epic cultural level to show
up to grow up to acknowledge our shadows
and to be present and that is is maybe
that's the evolutionary step that we
need to see but then also like you're
saying women need to acknowledge their
shadows as well yeah but I think that
was playing up perfectly in the
interview in in the sense that Kathy she
just got more and more angry and the
reason why what was missing out was a
masculine being present with her and
feeling her instead of just meeting her
with the mind because that's going to
feel overpowering if you feel if if
you're in your emotions and in your body
instead of being really present and say
I feel your rage I understand it so
that's where we can start moving on
because the feminine will feel seen she
will feel respected in that embodied
truth because yes women have something
to be enraged about for sure and we we
need that to become real and not to be
just become a power battle so yes women
test men to call them into presence and
embodiment and just an intellectual
conversation is not enough it's just
gonna keep stirring up the rage so we
need to find a way to have that
conversation where both the body the
deeper waste and the deeper intelligence
and the mind is there present on both
sides so that's what I mean about having
an intelligent conversation it's not
just the conversation of the mind it's a
conversation about what's real what's
aligned with life and that's a whole
different conversation it's a different
way of communicating so that's what
Jordan Peterson could have done better
in that interview is just to have said I
can feel where you're coming from I
think that could have changed the whole
energy the whole dynamic and it could
have moved it forward but it's
impossible to move it forward when we're
both in battle mode so yes if you want a
more direct experience of some of the
topics in this film rebel wisdom is
running workshops
men to grow up and show up more in the
world check the website for more great
films such as the first full-length
documentary on Jordan Peterson and for
details of our upcoming events
[Music]
you